In the Name of Allah we are staring
Al-salam Alekom
Peace be upon you
Let us talk about simple topology, consists of 4 hosts, two layer 2 simple switch, single router, single firewall.
sw_1 and sw_2 are layer 2. datapath id (unique) are 1 and 2
ro_1 is router datapath id (unique) is 21 in hexadecimal
fw_1 is firewall datapath id (unique) is 31 in hexadecimal
identify class of each ip.
host 1 and host 2 are in same class 10.0.0.2, 10.0.0.3 /24 for mask
host 3 and host 4 are in same class 100.0.0.2, 100.0.0.3 /8 for mask
sw_1 and sw_2 are layer 2. datapath id (unique) are 1 and 2
ro_1 is router datapath id (unique) is 21 in hexadecimal
fw_1 is firewall datapath id (unique) is 31 in hexadecimal
in order to run single ryu-manager session, I select fixed values for datapath id
controller which ryu will run on has ip 192.168.1 at port 6632
we have to modify official copy of rest_firewall, rest_router and simple switch layer 2.
as we have two networks, we must define gateway for each host.
h1,h2 gateway is 10.0.0.1
h3,h4 gateway is 100.0.0.1
our requirements are host1 can ping both h2, h3.
also our requirements are host2 can ping both h1, h4.
three putty terminals.
sudo mn -c; sudo python 3 topo_1.python
clear ; sudo ryu-manager ryu.app.ofctl_rest simple_switch_13_custom.py rest_router_custom.py rest_firewall_custom.py /home/ubuntu/sdn/sources/flowmanager/flowmanager.py --observe-links --ofp-tcp-listen-port 6632 --wsapi-port 8085
sh conf.sh
-------------
for ryu-manager
ryu.app.ofctl_rest
simple_switch_13_custom.py
rest_router_custom.py
rest_firewall_custom.py
flowmanager/flowmanager.py
--ofp-tcp-listen-port 6632
--wsapi-port 8085
In the name of Allah we are starting
once you run controller
take a look for flow table
switch 1,2 will have two roles (one for miss flow rule, other for flowmanager)
switch 33 will have configuration of firewall (controller, controller, drop , normal)
switch 49 will have configuration of router (controller drop, normal, controller)
let us run conf.sh through shell to see results.
after that we will run line by line as step by step
in breif
21 is router we need to add two ip addresses for both sides.
firewall needs to enables
firewall lines is enable newtork id 10.0.0.x to communicate to route via firewall
sh conf.sh
not found 33: has no importance.
neglect it
h1 can ping h2,h3
h2 can ping h1, h4
h3 to h2, h4
h4 to h2 ,h3
let us start again
sudo mn -c; sudo python3 topo_1.py
step by step
21 in hexadecimal.
note
src,dst 10.0.0.0/ 255.255.255.0 output is normal
some roles will be added after adding ip for router
same network can ping each other. as both in same network but firewall is located before router.
same line 100.0.0.1/8 for other router port
100.0.0.1/255.0.0.0
enable for firewall
drop line was removed from roles after enable firewall
enable h1/h2 to be able to ping gateway
h1 ,h2 , router to firewall is in same network class
10.0.0.0/255.255.255.0 output is normal now
h1 can ping router now
let us enable h1,h2 to ping other router port 100.0.0.1
let h1 ping 100.0.0.1
confirm src and dst to allow icmp
so
'{"nw_src": "10.0.0.1/24", "nw_dst": "100.0.0.1",
'{"nw_src": "100.0.0.1", "nw_dst": "10.0.0.1/24",
now h1, h2 can ping 100.0.0.1
let us allow h1 to ping h3
'{"nw_src": "10.0.0.2", "nw_dst": "100.0.0.2",
'{"nw_src": "100.0.0.2", "nw_dst": "10.0.0.2",
we don't add "/" as we specify single address to connect
All praise and Thanks To Allah
the rest is
let us allow h2 to ping h4
'{"nw_src": "10.0.0.3", "nw_dst": "100.0.0.3",
'{"nw_src": "100.0.0.3", "nw_dst": "10.0.0.3",
we don't add "/" as we specify single address to connect
before this line block occurs
pingall
the modification for official router / firewall/ simple switch
is
let us search by ahmed in file rest_firewall_custom.py
if(dp.id != 49):
returm
if datapath id not equal 49 leave without registering or adding any role
let us search by ahmed in file simple_switch_custom.py
if(dp.id >3):
return
if datapath id is greater than 3 leave without registering or adding any role
let us search by ahmed in file rest_router_custom.py
if(dp.id != 33):
return